with Professor Hiroshi Ishii, and we built this array of 512 different electromagnets, and together they were able to move objects around on top of their surface. But the problem with this was that these magnets cost over 10,000 dollars. Although each one was pretty small, altogether they weighed so much that the table that they were on started to sag. So I wanted to build something where you could have this kind of interaction on any tabletop surface. So to explore this idea, I built an army of small robots, and each of these robots has what are called omni wheels. They're these special wheels that can move equally easily in all directions, and when you couple these robots with a video projector, you have these physical tools for interacting with digital information. So here's an example of what I mean. This is a video editing application where all of the controls for manipulating the video are physical. So if we want to tweak the color, we just enter the color mode, and then we get three different dials for tweaking the color, or if we want to adjust the audio, then we get two different dials for that, these physical objects. So here the left and right channel stay in sync, but if we want to, we can override that by grabbing both of them at the same time. So the idea is that we get the speed and efficiency benefits of using these physical dials together with the flexibility and versatility of a system that's designed in software. And this is a mapping application for disaster response. So you have these physical objects that represent police, fire and rescue, and a dispatcher can grab them and place them on the map to tell those units where to go, and then the position of the units on the map gets synced up with the position of those units in the real world. This is a video chat application. It's amazing how much emotion you can convey with just a few simple movements of a physical object. With this interface, we open up a huge array of possibilities in between traditional board games and arcade games, where the physical possibilities of interaction make so many different styles of play possible. But one of the areas that I'm most excited about using this platform for is applying it to problems that are difficult for computers or people to solve alone. One example of those is protein folding. So here we have an interface where we have physical handles onto a protein, and we can grab those handles and try to move the protein and try to fold it in different ways. And if we move it in a way that doesn't really make sense with the underlying molecular simulation, we get this physical feedback where we can actually feel these physical handles pulling back against us. So feeling what's going on inside a molecular simulation is a whole different level of interaction. So we're just beginning to explore what's possible when we use software to control the movement of objects in our environment. Maybe this is the computer of the future. There's no touchscreen. There's no technology visible at all. But when we want to have a video chat or play a game or lay out the slides to our next TED Talk, the objects on the table come alive. Thank you. (Applause)
con el profesor Hiroshi Ishii. Construimos esta configuración de 512 electroimanes. Juntos podían mover objetos sobre su superficie. Pero el problema con esto era que los imanes cuestan más de USD 10 000. Si bien cada uno era bastante pequeño, juntos pesaban tanto que la mesa que los sostenía empezó a ceder. Yo quería construir algo que permitiera este tipo de interacciones sobre cualquier superficie de mesa. Por eso, para explorar esta idea construí un ejército de pequeños robots y cada uno de estos robots tiene lo que llamamos omniruedas. Son ruedas especiales que pueden moverse por igual en cualquier dirección, y cuando se dota a estos robots de un videoproyector, se obtienen estas herramientas físicas para interactuar con información digital. Este es un ejemplo de lo que quiero decir. Esta es una aplicación para editar video en la que todos los controles para manipular el video son físicos. Si queremos retocar el color, entramos al modo color, y tenemos 3 diales para retocar el color. Si queremos ajustar el audio, tenemos 2 diales para hacerlo, con estos objetos físicos. Aquí los canales izquierdo y derecho están sincronizados pero si queremos, podemos sobrescribir eso agarrando ambos al mismo tiempo. La idea es conseguir la velocidad y la eficiencia de usar estos diales físicos junto a la flexibilidad y versatilidad de un sistema diseñado en software. Y esta es una aplicación cartográfica para respuesta a desastres. Uno tiene estos objetos físicos que representan la policía, los bomberos y el equipo de rescate, y un despachador puede agarrarlos y ubicarlos en el mapa para decirle a esas unidades dónde ir, y entonces la posición de las unidades en el mapa se sincroniza con la posición de esas unidades en el mundo real. Esta es una aplicación de videochat. Es increíble la cantidad de emociones que se pueden transmitir con pocos movimientos simples de un objeto físico. Con esta interfaz, abrimos un enorme abanico de posibilidades entre los juegos de mesa tradicionales y los juegos de arcade, donde las posibilidades físicas de interacción dan lugar a muchos estilos diferentes de jugar. Pero una de las áreas que más me entusiasma es el uso de esta plataforma en problemas difíciles de resolver para computadoras o personas por separado. Un ejemplo es el plegamiento de proteínas. Aquí tenemos una interfaz para manipular las proteínas, podemos agarrar las asas para tratar de mover la proteína y plegarla de distintas maneras. Y si la movemos en una forma que no tiene sentido, con la simulación molecular subyacente obtenemos esta respuesta física y sentimos estas asas físicas que nos empujan hacia atrás. Así, sentir lo que ocurre dentro de una simulación molecular es un nivel totalmente diferente de interacción. Apenas empezamos a explorar las posibilidades de usar software para controlar el movimiento de objetos en nuestro entorno. Quizá esta sea la computadora del futuro. No hay pantalla táctil. No hay tecnología visible, en absoluto. Pero cuando queremos hacer un videochat o jugar un juego o diseñar las diapositivas para nuestra próxima charla TED los objetos de la mesa cobran vida. Gracias. (Aplausos)